there's a brand spanking new study
that's making the rounds because it
seems at first glance to indicate
vitamin D and Omega-3s slow down aging
but there's some nuances to be had
because there's more to this than the
catchy headline in this study
researchers analyzed the data coming
from a larger group of participants that
they had split into eight conditions
here they are vitamin D only omega-3
only X exercise only vitamin D plus
omega-3 vitamin D exercise omega-3
exercise all treatments combined and of
course a placebo the participants
underwent each intervention for 3 years
and the researchers took blood samples
before and after the 3 years with these
samples the researchers performed an
epigenetic array which is a type of
experiment where the researchers can
identify which genes in your genome are
tagged with methyl groups meaning
they've been methylated methylation
changes if a gene can or can't be read
since we know the methylation pattern
across the genome as we age we can
compare a person's individual results to
the Genome of the 50-year-old a
55-year-old a 60-year-old and so on
comparing the methylation pattern of a
person to these Banks of methylation
patterns that are linked to
chronological age gives scientists A
View on how old a person's biological
age is at least based on methylation so
you might be I don't know 73 but your
methylation patterns May return a result
that indicates that you're actually 64
years old so now that we understand that
what happened to these people if we look
at that data there's four different
methylation tests the pheno age the Grim
age version one and two as well as that
dunid in pace which always makes me want
to say it in a butchered Irish accent we
can see the different conditions and
importantly what they're compared
against on the left side of each test
finally we see the zero line there which
indicates no likely effect the black
boxes indicate the estimated effect and
the lines indicate in simple terms the
certainty of the result or effect where
95% certain the effect is within these
lines if the results move to the left
that indicates A reduced biological age
or Pace of Aging depending on the test
so there's a few notable findings here
one vitamin D had no effect in all
comparisons of vitamin D supplementation
versus no vitamin D supplementation
across all four tests no effect
surprisingly at least to me exercise
also had no effect on its own however
while those two interventions seem to
disappoint Omega-3s provided some
positive news across three of the tests
consuming Omega-3s did provide a slowing
of the pace of Aging it even catapulted
vitamin D in exercise from a no effect
to indicating an effect but we likely
can't attribute that to vitamin D or
exercise since the main driver is likely
omega3 consumption okay that data is
pretty revealing but there's some
nuances that we still need to go over
including how much of each to use and
exactly how big the effect is this is
seldom discussed first if we look at the
data we're looking again at the good old
dunan Pace but this time the researchers
are performing a subgroup analysis that
means that they're splitting the groups
apart based on some characteristic in
this case blood omega-3 levels the left
graph is for those with lower blood
omega-3 levels and the right is for
those that already have higher omega-3
levels again if we focus on the omega-3
versus no omega-3 comparison again we
see that only those that have lower
blood values experience a benefit this
makes reasonable sense since a person
might be already eating more fatty fish
reaping some of the benefits already as
just one example so to be clear I've
isolated those data because the other
tests do not show any effect although
the pheno age test gets very close to
the same conclusion at any rate there's
some evidence but it isn't Universal so
this would imply that if your blood
levels of Omega-3 or lower supplementing
or consuming omega-3 rich foods would be
especially beneficial for you and may be
unnecessary if your blood values are
higher at least based on these aging
measures actually one more quick thing
related to this uh you don't actually
have to get your blood levels checked
although that's the most exact way you
can just look at your diet and ask if
you consume fatty fish like salmon twice
a week or if you already supplement if
not then chances are you're falling into
that camp that might benefit I'm going
to be doing more of this kind of
subgroup analysis especially on vitamin
D and Omega-3s and getting into the
weeds in The Insider version of this
video it's an Extended Cut of the video
that you're watching if you're
interested along with access to all my
in-depth analyses the link for the
physionic Insiders where the video is is
in the description of this video check
it out okay now two more things that we
need to discuss along with some nuances
dosing and effect size so if we pop open
the first sequence of data you'll note
that the numbers on the horizontal axis
they don't correspond to anything
directly they're called standardized
treatment effects which means nothing to
anyone unless you back calculate and get
the understandable results the
researchers did do the back calculation
and the effect is around 3. 8 months
slower Aging in the best case scenario
that means that after 3 years the
participants could achieve a methylation
pattern that is about 4 months younger
now to contextualize that one we're
generally discussing pretty easy
interventions two 4 months might not
seem like a lot and some might think
that it's nothing well one uh none of
the participants are Benjamin Button and
two consider that it's only 3 years so
the effect would likely become more
noticeable over time as is often the
case with long duration effects also
keep in mind that the participants are
already in their mid-70s so the effect
might be bigger or smaller for younger
individuals okay so what do we take away
from all this and how much did the
researchers give these people in the end
this is one measure of aging and I think
some would fairly argue that it's
insufficient to adequately address aging
as a whole but it's one major way to
address it that caveat mentioned omega-3
consumption has the most robust evidence
in favor of its age slowing effect with
vitamin D being less impressive as well
as the exercise routine implemented that
may be a slightly different story when
they're all consumed together so if
you're looking for the simple root 1 G
of Omega-3 a day was used in the study
and indicated robust Effectiveness for
one simple intervention now if you're
looking for a whole package the same
amount of Omega-3 paired with 2,000 IU
vitamin D and simple full body strength
training exercises 3 times per week for
30 minutes per session will do the trick
but rest assured the majority of the
effect is driven by Omega-3s and
speaking of Omega-3s I have a bunch of
content going over the science
right here thanks for watching and I'll
speak with you over there
[Music]